Guide to the Hanover Royal Music Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Hanover royal music archive
1651-1951
1770-1870
OSB MSS 146
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
30.09
(902 boxes)
The Hanover Royal Music Archive consists of printed and manuscript music, printed books about music, and related materials assembled by Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover, and his successors. A significant component originated in England and concerns musical activity of several children of George III, circa 1770-1837, particularly Ernest Augustus, then Duke of Cumberland, and Princess Augusta, as well as Prince George of Cumberland, son of Ernest Augustus and later Georg V, King of Hanover. These materials moved to Hanover, apparently circa 1837 when Ernest Augustus succeeded William IV as King of Hanover. In Hanover, the collection was expanded by Ernest Augustus and Georg V, and much of the present content relates to music in the Hanoverian court through the mid-nineteenth century. While most materials date circa 1770-1870, a few items extend this span from the seventeenth through the mid-twentieth century.
Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover, 1771-1851
Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782 ( Concertos, harpsichord, string orchestra, op. 1)
Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782 ( Gioas, rè di Giuda, T'adoro te solo eterno mio Dio)
Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782 ( Sonatas, flute, harpsichord, op. 16)
Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782 ( Sonatas, harpsichord, flute, cello, op. 2)
Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782 ( Sonatas, harpsichord, op. 5)
Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782 ( Sonatas, harpsichord, op. 17)
Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782 ( Sonatas, violin, keyboard instrument, op. 10)
Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750 ( Edwards music reprints, Series A, No. 1, Complete works and monumenta, Johann Sebastian Bach's Werke)
Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 ( 25 Schottische Lieder)
Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 ( Grand sonate pathétique)
Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 ( Sonata, piano, no. 17, op. 31, no. 2, D minor)
Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 ( Symphonies, no. 1, op. 21, C major)
Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827 ( Trios, piano, strings, op. 1)
Berlioz, Hector, 1803-1869 ( Grand death-mass)
Berlioz, Hector, 1803-1869 ( Te Deum, op. 22)
Clementi, Muzio, 1752-1832 ( Chasse, piano)
Clementi, Muzio, 1752-1832 ( Sonatas, harpsichord, op. 23)
Clementi, Muzio, 1752-1832 ( Sonatas, piano, op. 25)
Clementi, Muzio, 1752-1832 ( Sonatas, harpsichord, flute, cello, op. 21)
Clementi, Muzio, 1752-1832 ( Clementi's op. 22)
Clementi, Muzio, 1752-1832 ( Sonatas and a duet, op. 12)
Georg, King of Hannover, V, 1819-1878 ( Ideen und Betrachtungen über die Eigenschaften der Musik)
Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759 ( Acis and Galatea, HWV 49a)
Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759 ( Esther, HWV 50a, Overture, arranged)
Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759 ( Anthem for the funeral of Queen Caroline)
Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759 ( Hallelujah Handel)
Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759 ( Cantate e sonate da camera)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Schöpfung, arranged)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( 12 London symphonies)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Londoner Sinfonie, no. 6)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Londoner Sinfonie, no. 1)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Londoner Sinfonie, no. 4)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Londoner Sinfonie, no. 10)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Londoner Sinfonie, no. 12, G major)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Cloches)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Quartets, flute, violin, viola, cello, no. 3, B♭ major)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Symphonies, H. I, 103, E♭ major, arranged)
Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809 ( Favorite sonata)
Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847 ( 7 pieces in the form of a suite)
Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847 ( 95. Psalm)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Clemenza di Tito, Vocal score)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Clemenza di Tito, Ouverture, arranged)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Divertimenti, K. 247, F major)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Deuxième musique de nuit lodronienne)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Don Giovanni, Vocal score)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Finta giardiniera)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Idomeneo, Ouverture)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Nozze di Figaro, Ouverture)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Arias & duets)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Frühling, violins (2), viola, cello)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Quartet, strings, K. 417b (421), D minor)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Caccia)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Grand quintetto, K. 516)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Quintets, violins (2), violas (2), cello, K. 593, D major)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Quintets, violins (2), violas (2), cello, K. 614, E♭ major, arranged)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Impresario overture)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Paris)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Trios, piano, strings, K. 564, G major)
Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Magic flute overture)
Pleyel, Ignaz, 1757-1831 ( Sonatas, harpsichord, violin, cello, B. 437-439)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Barbiere di Siviglia, Sinfonia, arranged)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Cenerentola, Sinfonia, arranged)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Donna del lago, Vocal score)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Gazza ladra, Vocal score)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Mosè in Egitto, Vocal score)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Otello, Sinfonia, arranged)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Semiramide, Vocal score)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Tancredi, Vocal score)
Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868 ( Turco in Italia, Sinfonia, arranged)
Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, 1712-1778 ( Devin du village, Selections)
Strauss, Johann, 1804-1849 ( Waltzes, piano, Selections)
Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 ( Euryanthe, Ouvertüre, arranged)
Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 ( Freischütz, Vocal score)
Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 ( Freischütz, Ouverture, arranged)
Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 ( Oberon, arranged)
Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 ( Oberon, Overture, arranged)
Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 ( Preciosa, Ouvertüre, arranged)
Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826 ( Sonatas, piano, J. 138, C major)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Formerly owned by Ernst August, Prince of Hanover. Purchased from Sotheby's on the Hazel M. Osborn Fund and the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2008. For more information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 339 Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Historical Notes
Hanover became an electorate of the Holy Roman Empire in 1692. In 1714, George I succeeded as both King of Great Britain and Elector of Hanover, establishing a personal union of the two titles that continued through the eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. Hanover became a kingdom in 1814, ruled by George III, King of Great Britain, and his successors George IV and William IV. When William IV was succeeded by Queen Victoria in 1837, the prohibition of female succession under Hanoverian law ended the personal union between Britain and Hanover, and Ernest Augustus, Duke of Cumberland, eighth of fifteen children of George III, became Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover. At the same time, Ernest Augustus's son, Prince George of Cumberland, became Georg, Crown Prince of Hanover. The Crown Prince succeeded his father as Georg V, King of Hanover, in 1851.
Musicians working at the court of George III included Johann Christian Bach, who served as music master to Queen Charlotte, 1763-1782, Johann Samuel Schroeter, and Charles Frederick Horn, who served as music instructor for the princesses, 1789-1812. Both Ernest Augustus and Georg V had strong musical interests: Ernest Augustus employed a private band in England as the Duke of Cumberland, and Georg composed and wrote about music. Georg V apparently continued to compose after moving to Hanover, although injuries to his eyes had resulted in blindness by 1833.
Hanover was annexed by Prussia in 1866, as a consequence of the Austro-Prussian War. Georg V lived the remainder of his life in exile in Austria and France, without renouncing his Hanoverian title. His son, Ernst August (1845-1923), continued to claim succession rights, while holding the title of Duke of Cumberland and Teviotdale. Ernest Augustus was deprived of this title after siding with Germany during Word War I. His son, Ernst August (1887-1953), Duke of Brunswick from 1913, was forced to abdicate in 1918.
Below is a chronology of key dates and a list of members of the British and Hanoverian royal families represented in the collection.
Chronology
Dates following names refer to reigns or titles held.
1692-1806 Braunschweig-Lüneburg, also called Hanover, an electorate of the Holy Roman Empire
1714 personal union between Great Britain and Hanover started George I, King of Great Britain and Elector of Hanover, 1714-1727
1727 George II, King of Great Britain and Elector of Hanover, 1727-1760
1760 George III, King of Great Britain and Elector of Hanover, 1760-1820
1806 Hanover annexed by France
1811 George IV, Prince Regent of Great Britain, 1811-1820
1814 Kingdom of Hanover established
1820 George IV, King of Great Britain and King of Hanover, 1820-1830
1830 William IV, King of Great Britain and King of Hanover, 1830-1837
1837 Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover, 1837-1851 Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1837-1901 personal union between Great Britain and Hanover ended
1851 Georg V, King of Hanover, 1851-1866
1866 Austro-Prussian War; Hanover annexed by Prussia Georg V exiled, 1866-1878
1878 Ernst August (1845-1923), Duke of Cumberland and Teviotdale, 1878-1913, and pretender to Hanoverian throne, 1878-
1913 Ernst August (1887-1953), Duke of Brunswick, 1913-1918
1918 Ernst August (1887-1953), abdicated as Duke of Brunswick
1919 Ernst August (1845-1923), deprived of titles in the United Kingdom
Royal Family of Great Britain
Date spans in parentheses are birth/death dates; other date spans refer to reigns or titles held.
George III (1738–1820)
King of Great Britain, 1760-1820
Married: Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Strelitz (1744–1818)
Successor: George IV
Children:
-----George IV (1762-1830)
----------Prince of Wales, 1762-1820
----------Prince Regent, 1811-1820
----------King of Great Britain, 1820-1830
----------Married: Princess Caroline of Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel (1768-1821)
----------Successor: William IV
-----Frederick Augustus, Duke of York (1763-1827)
----------Married: Princess Frederica Charlotte of Prussia
-----William IV (1765-1837)
----------King of Great Britain, 1830-1837
----------Married: Adelaide of Saxe-Meiningen (1792-1849)
----------Successor: Victoria
-----Charlotte Augusta Matilda, Princess Royal (1766-1828)
----------Queen of Württemberg, 1806-1816
----------Queen Dowager of Württemberg, 1816-1828
----------Married: Frederick I, King of Württemberg (1754-1816)
-----Edward, Duke of Kent and Strathearn (1767-1820)
----------Married: Princess Victoria of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld (1786-1861)
-----Princess Augusta Sophia (1768-1840)
-----Princess Elizabeth (1770-1840)
----------Landgravine of Hesse-Homburg, 1820-1840
----------Married: Frederick VI, Landgrave of Hesse-Homburg
-----Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover (1771-1851)
----------Duke of Cumberland and Teviotdale, 1799-1837
----------King of Hanover, 1827-1851
----------Married: Friederike Caroline Sophia Alexandrina of Solms-Braunfels (1778–1841)
-----Augustus Frederick, Duke of Sussex (1773-1843)
----------Married: Lady Augusta Murray (1761-1830)
----------Married: Lady Cecilia Gore (1793-1873)
-----Adolphus, Duke of Cambridge (1774-1850)
----------Married: Princess Augusta Wilhelmina Louisa of Hesse-Cassel (1797-1889)
----------Heir: Prince George, Duke of Cambridge (1819-1904)
-----Princess Mary (1776-1857)
----------Duchess of Gloucester and Edinburgh, 1816-1857
----------Married: Prince William Frederick, Duke of Gloucester and Edinburgh (1776-1834)
-----Princess Sophia (1777-1848)
-----Prince Octavius (1779-1783)
-----Prince Alfred (1780-1782)
-----Princess Amelia (1783-1810)
Royal Family of Hanover
George I, King of Great Britain, 1714-1727, and Elector of Hanover, 1698-1727
George II, King of Great Britain and Elector of Hanover, 1727-1760
George III, King of Great Britain and Hanover, 1760-1820 (see above)
George IV, King of Great Britain and Hanover, 1820-1830 (see above)
William IV, King of Great Britain and Hanover, 1830-1837 (see above)
Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover, 1837-1851 (see above)
Georg V (1819-1878)
Prince George of Cumberland, 1819-1837
Crown Prince of Hanover, 1837-1851
King of Hanover, 1851-1866
Exiled, 1866-1878
Married: Princess Marie Alexandrina of Saxe-Altenburg (1818–1878)
Children:
-----Ernst August (1845-1923) (see below)
-----Princess Frederica (1848-1926)
----------Baroness von Pawel-Rammingen, 1880-1926
----------Married: Baron Alfons von Pawel-Rammingen
-----Princess Marie (1849-1904)
Ernst August (1845-1923)
-----Crown Prince of Hanover, 1851-1866
-----pretender to Hanoverian throne, 1878-
-----Duke of Cumberland and Teviotdale, 1878-1919
-----Married: Princess Thyra of Denmark
Ernst August (1887-1953)
-----Duke of Brunswick, 1913-1918
-----Married: Princess Victoria Louise of Prussia
Ernst August (1914-1987)
-----Married: Ortrud of Schleswig-Holstein-Sonderburg-Glücksburg
-----Married: Monika of Solms-Laubach
Ernst August (1954-)
Ernst August (1983-)
Scope and Contents
The Hanover Royal Music Archive consists of printed and manuscript music, printed books about music, and related materials assembled by Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover, and his successors. A significant component originated in England and concerns musical activity of several children of George III, circa 1770-1837, particularly Ernest Augustus, then Duke of Cumberland, and Princess Augusta, as well as Prince George of Cumberland, son of Ernest Augustus and later Georg V, King of Hanover. These materials moved to Hanover, apparently circa 1837 when Ernest Augustus succeeded William IV as King of Hanover. In Hanover, the collection was expanded by Ernest Augustus and Georg V, and much of the present content relates to music in the Hanoverian court through the mid-nineteenth century. While most materials date circa 1770-1870, a few items extend this span from the seventeenth through the mid-twentieth century.
Contents include manuscript and printed music used in performance; manuscript music books and bound collections; music in presentation bindings, inscribed or accompanied by letters from composers to Ernest Augustus, Georg V, or other royal family members; and books about music theory and pedagogy. Many genres of music are present, with concentrations in song, collections of national songs of Great Britain and Ireland, solo keyboard, chamber ensemble parts, sacred vocal music scores and parts, opera in vocal score, military band parts, and keyboard and ensemble music for marches, waltzes, and other social dance. Music of a wide range of both major and lesser-known composers active in England, Germany, and elsewhere in Europe during the eighteenth through mid-nineteenth century is present, including early printed editions of Johann Christian Bach, Haydn, Clementi, Mozart, Beethoven, Weber, Rossini, Berlioz, Johann Strauss, Sr., Mendelssohn. Many items bear marks of ownership, including presentation inscriptions, signatures, annotations, shelf mark labels, stamps, personalized and presentation bindings, and accompanying correspondence.
Among materials originating in England are manuscript music books of Princess Augusta and other royal family members, containing holograph music of Johann Christian Bach and Charles Frederick Horn, and an extensive archive of music performed by a private band employed by Ernest Augustus while Duke of Cumberland. Most material added in Hanover consists of presentation copies of music dedicated to Georg V; Hanoverian and Prussian military band music; literary papers, music drafts, and published music of Georg V; and music performed by the Hof- and Kirchenchor, including an archive of manuscript liturgical music. Later additions to the collection include music dedicated to Ernst August (1845-1923) and to members of the Prussian royal family. Additions dated circa 1860s-1910s are predominantly sacred music, indicating that the collection may have remained in use by church musicians during that period.
The archive documents music of the British and Hanoverian royal courts during the period of its accumulation, and is a resource for study of individual music manuscripts and rare publications. Materials originating in Great Britain are related to content dating from the same time period in the British Library's Royal Music Library of Great Britain, and may be found to fill gaps in that larger collection. Several strengths of the Hanover collection are the smaller archives contained within it, particularly music of the Duke of Cumberland's band, Hanover liturgical manuscripts, and music and literary papers of Georg V. Aspects of broad research value include: Johann Christian Bach and his circle; other individual composers and their published and unpublished work; music in the royal courts of Great Britain and Hanover; members of the British and Hanoverian royal families; composition, music education, and professional and amateur performance and employment of musicians in England and Germany; and manuscript copying, music printing, binding practices, and the music trade.
Notes on Folder Description
Folder titles for music are in a standardized format, consisting of the following as appropriate: truncated transcribed title; type of score and list of parts; holograph, manuscript, or print; and place and publisher. Contents not listed individually by Sotheby's have been described briefly, usually as "music," either manuscript or print. For all contents, full names and birth/death dates in headings have been supplied, if found in the Library of Congress Authority File or The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, or in materials in the collection. While these names are generally of composers or authors, some materials are listed under arrangers, editors, or compilers, in conformance with original folders or shelfmark labels.
Much of the manuscript material is copyist's manuscript; some holograph manuscripts have been identified, and others are likely present. Most printed music is engraved, unless noted as typeset or lithograph. Full or partial uniform titles have been added to some folder titles, and some see/see also references have been supplied. Vocal and instrumental parts are listed as found, with no attempt to determine if sets are complete. The following abbreviations have been used in lists of parts:
v (voice), vv (voices) SATBarB (soprano, alto, tenor, baritone, bass)
kbd (keyboard), pf (piano), hpd (harpsichord)
picc (piccolo), fl (flute), ob (oboe), cl (clarinet), bn (bassoon), spt (serpent)
hn (horn), tpt (trumpet), trbn (trombone)
timp (timpani)
hp (harp)
vn (violin), va (viola), vc (violoncello), db (double bass)
b (bass)
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. General Music and Books About Music, 1714-1951. II. Music Collections, 1651-1868. III. Duke of Cumberland's Band Archive, circa 1765-1834. IV. Hanover Liturgical Manuscripts, 1859-1867. V. Notes of Former Owners, [1980s?]-2005.
Band music; Chamber music; Choruses, Sacred; Composers -- England; Composers -- Germany; Dance music; Marches; Military music; Music -- Germany -- 18th century; Music -- Germany -- 19th century; Music -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Music -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Music publishing -- Germany; Music publishing -- Great Britain; Music trade -- Germany; Music trade -- Great Britain; Operas; Orchestral music; Piano music; Sacred vocal music; Songs, English; Songs with piano; Symphonies; Vocal music; Waltzes; Great Britain -- History -- George III, 1760-1820; Great Britain -- History -- George IV, 1820-1830; Great Britain -- History -- William IV, 1830-1837; Hannover (Germany); Hannover (Germany) -- History -- 19th century; Abingdon, Willoughby Bertie, Earl of, 1740-1799; Abrams, Miss, approximately 1758-1821; Abt, Franz, 1819-1885; Adam, Adolphe, 1803-1856; Alfieri, Pietro, 1801-1863; Allegri, Gregorio, 1582-1652; Amelia, Princess, daughter of George III, King of Great Britain, 1783-1810; Ander, Alois, 1821-1864; André, Anton; Angely, Louis, 1787-1835; Antony, Joseph, 1790-1837; Arditi, Luigi, 1822-1903; Arne, Thomas Augustine, 1710-1778; Arnold, F. W.; Arnold, Samuel, 1740-1802; Asioli, Bonifazio, 1769-1832; Astorga, Emanuele, barone d', 1680-; Attwood, Thomas, 1765-1838; Auber, D. F. E. (Daniel François Esprit), 1782-1871; Augusta Sophia, Princess, daughter of George III, King of Great Britain, 1768-1840; Bach, Johann Christian, 1735-1782; Bach, Johann Christoph, 1642-1703; Bach, Johann Michael, 1648-1694; Bach, Johann Sebastian, 1685-1750; Balfe, M. W. (Michael William), 1808-1870; Barthélemon, F.-H. (François-Hippolyte), 1741-1808; Barthelemon, Mary, 1749-1799; Bausset, Alexandre de; Bazzini, Antonio, 1818-1897; Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827; Bellini, Vincenzo, 1801-1835; Bennett, William Sterndale, 1816-1875; Berlioz, Hector, 1803-1869; Bianchi, F. (Francesco), approximately 1752-1810; Bishop, Henry R. (Henry Rowley), 1786-1855; Blangini, Felice, 1781-1841; Blumenstengel, A.; Boccherini, Luigi, 1743-1805; Bochsa, Robert Nicolas Charles, 1789-1856; Böhme, H.; Böhmer, Carl; Böhner, Johann Ludwig, 1787-1860; Boieldieu, A. (Adrien), 1775-1834; Bossi, Cesare, 1773-1802; Bott, J. J. (Jean Joseph), 1826-1895; Boyce, William, 1711-1779; Braham, John, 1774-1856; Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897; Branzoli, Giuseppe, 1835-1909; Bréval, J. B. (Jean Baptiste), 1753-1823; Brooks, James, approximately 1757-1819; Busby, Thomas, 1754-1838; Cahusac, William; Caldara, Antonio, 1670-1736; Callcott, John Wall, 1766-1821; Callcott, William H. (William Hutchins), 1807-1882; Camidge, Matthew, 1764?-1844; Campagnoli, Bartolomeo, 1751-1827; Campbell, Caroline, active 18th century; Cantone, Carlo, active 18th century; Carafa, Michele, 1787-1872; Carbonel, N. (Narcisse), 1773-1855; Cardon, Jean-Baptiste, 1760-1803; Chambers, Miss (Marianne), active 1799-1811; Charlotte, Queen, consort of George III, King of Great Britain, 1744-1818; Cherubini, Luigi, 1760-1842; Chrysander, Friedrich, 1826-1901; Cimarosa, Domenico, 1749-1801; Clarke-Whitfeld, John, 1770-1836; Clementi, Muzio, 1752-1832; Commer, Franz, 1813-1887; Cooke, T. (Thomas), 1782-1848; Corri, Montague, 1784-1849; Cramer, J. B. (Johann Baptist), 1771-1858; Croft, William, 1678-1727; Curschmann, Fr. (Friedrich), 1805-1841; Da Ponte, Lorenzo, 1749-1838; Dahmen, Johan Arnold, 1766-1812; Dale, Joseph, 1750-1821; Damcke, Berthold, 1812-1875; Dauverné, François Georges Auguste, 1799-1874; Dessauer, Josef, 1798-1876; Devienne, François, 1759-1803; Dittersdorf, Karl Ditters von, 1739-1799; Donizetti, Gaetano, 1797-1848; Donizetti, Giuseppe, 1788-1856; Dommer, Arrey von, 1828-1905; Doppler, Franz, 1821-1883; Dreyschock, Alexander, 1818-1869; Dussek, Johann Ladislaus, 1760-1812; Durante, Francesco, 1684-1755; Eckert, Karl Anton Florian, 1820-1879; Edelmann, Jean-Frédéric, 1749-1794; Eggeling, Eduard, 1813-1885; Egloffstein, Caroline von, 1789-1868; Egville, J.-H. d', 1773-; Ehrlich, C. F., 1807-1887; Eler, André-Frédéric, 1764-1821; Elizabeth, Princess of England, 1770-1840; Ellerton, John Lodge, 1801-1873; Elouis, J. (Joseph), 1752-approximately 1817; Enckhausen, Heinrich Friedrich, 1799-1885; Erfurt, Carl, 1807-1856; Erk, Ludwig, 1807-1883; Ernest Augustus, King of Hanover, 1771-1851; Ernst, Duke of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, II, 1818-1893; Ernst, H. W. (Heinrich Wilhelm), 1814-1865; Ernst August, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg, 1845-1923; Esch, Louis von; Falkland, Amelia Fitz Clarence Cary, Viscountess, 1803-1858; Favart, M. (Charles-Simon), 1710-1792; Fiorillo, Federigo, 1755-approximately 1823; Fischer, Michael Gotthard, 1773-1829; Flügel, Gustav, 1812-1900; Forkel, Johann Nikolaus, 1749-1818; Franck, Eduard, 1817-1893; Frike, Joseph, 1740-1798; Gabrielski, Johann Wilhelm, 1791-1846; Gade, Niels W. (Niels Wilhelm), 1817-1890; Gebauer, Étienne François, 1777-1823; Gebauer, François-René, 1773-1845; Gebauer, Michel Joseph, 1763-1812; Geissler, Carl, 1802-1869; Geminiani, Francesco, 1687-1762; Georg, King of Hannover, V, 1819-1878; Gerber, Ernst Ludwig, 1746-1819; Gevaert, F. A. (François Auguste), 1828-1908; Geyer, Fl. (Flodoard), 1811-1872; Giornovichi, Giovanni Mane, 1745-1804; Gluck, Christoph Willibald, Ritter von, 1714-1787; Goltermann, Georg, 1824-1898; Gounod, Charles, 1818-1893; Gow, Nathaniel, 1763-1831; Gow, Niel, 1727-1807; Greatorex, Thomas, 1758-1831; Greef, Wilhelm; Grétry, André-Ernest-Modeste, 1741-1813; Griesbach, John Henry, 1798-1875; Groom, Mrs. (Martha), -1867; Guidi, Francesco; Gurlitt, Cornelius, 1820-1901; Gyrowetz, Adalbert, 1763-1850; Hammerschmidt, Andreas, 1611 or 1612-1675; Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759; Hässler, Johann Wilhelm, 1747-1822; Hauptmann, Moritz, 1792-1868; Hawes, William, 1785-1846; Haydn, Joseph, 1732-1809; Heije, J. P. (Jan Pieter), 1809-1876; Hellmesberger, Georg, 1800-1873; Herrmann, Gottfried, 1808-1878; Herschel, Caroline Lucretia, 1750-1848; Hertel, Peter Ludwig, 1817-1899; Himmel, Friedrich Heinrich, 1765-1814; Hodges, Mrs. (Ann Mary), -1797; Hoffmeister, Franz Anton, 1754-1812; Holder, J. W. (Joseph William), 1764-1832; Honauer, Leontzi, approximately 1730-approximately 1790; Horecki, Feliks, 1796-1870; Horn, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1786-1849; Horn, Charles Frederick, 1762-1830; Horsley, William, 1774-1858; Hüllmandel, Nicolas-Joseph, 1756-1823; Hummel, Johann Nepomuk, 1778-1837; Jadin, Hyacinthe, 1776-1800; Jaëll, Alfred, 1832-1882; Jahn, Otto, 1813-1869; Jähns, Friedrich Wilhelm, 1809-1888; Jansen, F. Gustav, 1831-1910; Johnson, James, approximately 1750-1811; Jommelli, Nicolò, 1714-1774; Jones, Edward, 1752-1824; Jones, John, 1728-1796; Jones, William, 1726-1800; Kéler, Béla, 1820-1882; Kelly, Michael, 1762-1826; Kemp, Joseph, 1778-1824; Kern, Carl August, 1836-1897; Kjerulf, Halfdan, 1815-1868; Klein, Bernhard, 1793-1832; Kletzer, Feri; Knyvett, Charles, 1773-1852; Koch, Eduard Emil, 1809-1871; Kollmann, Augustus Frederic Christopher, 1756-1829; Kospoth, Otto Carl Erdmann, Freiherr von, 1753-1817; Kozeluch, Leopold, 1747-1818; Kretzschmer, A. (Andreas), 1775-1839; Kreutzer, Rodolphe, 1766-1831; Krommer, Franz, 1759-1831; Kücken, Friedrich Wilhelm, 1810-1882; Kühmstedt, Friedrich, 1809-1858; Kurpiński, Karol, 1785-1857; Labitzky, Joseph, 1802-1881; Lachner, Franz, 1803-1890; Lang, Josephine, 1815-1880; Lasso, Orlando di, 1532-1594; Latour, T., 1766-1837; Léonard, Hubert, 1819-1890; Lindner, August, 1820-1878; Lindpaintner, Peter Joseph von, 1791-1856; Linwood, Mary, 1755-1845; Liszt, Franz, 1811-1886; Logier, J. B. (Johann Bernhard), 1777-1846; Mainvielle-Fodor, Mme. (Joséphine), 1789-1870; Mannstein, H. F. (Heinrich Ferdinand); Marschner, Heinrich, 1795-1861; Marshall, William, 1749-1833; Martín y Soler, Vicente, 1754-1806; Martini, Johann Paul Aegidius, 1741-1816; Mary, Duchess of Gloucester, 1776-1857; Mattheson, Johann, 1681-1764; Mayr, Giovanni Simone, 1763-1845; Mazzinghi, Joseph, 1765-1844; Méhul, Etienne Nicolas, 1763-1817; Meluzzi, Salvatore, 1813-1897; Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847; Mengozzi, Bernardo, 1758-1800; Methfessel, Albert Gottlieb, 1785-1869; Mettenleiter, Dominicus, 1822-1868; Meyerbeer, Giacomo, 1791-1864; Miles, Thomas, approximately 1780-approximately 1852; Miller, Edward, 1735-1807; Mombelli, Domenico, 1751-1835; Monzani, Tebaldo, 1762-1839; Moscheles, Ignaz, 1794-1870; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; Mueller von Asow, E. H. (Erich Hermann), 1892-1964; Müller, Wenzel, 1759-1835; Napier, William, 1740?-1812; Negri, Benedetto, 1784-1854; Neithardt, A. (August), 1793-1861; Onslow, Georges, 1784-1853; Ortigue, Joseph d', 1802-1866; Oswald, James, 1710-1769; Paër, Ferdinando, 1771-1839; Page, John, approximately 1760-1812; Paisiello, Giovanni, 1740-1816; Palestrina, Giovanni Pierluigi da, 1525?-1594; Pannenberg, Friedrich Wilhelm; Panofka, Heinrich, 1807-1887; Panormo, F. C. (Ferdinand Charles); Panormo, Francis, 1764-1844; Panseron, Auguste-Mathieu, 1795-1859; Parke, William Thomas, 1762-1847; Pepusch, John Christopher, 1667-1752; Perez, David, 1711-1778; Piatti, Alfredo C. (Alfredo Carlo), 1822-1901; Piccinni, Niccolò, 1728-1800; Playford, Henry, 1657-; Pleyel, Ignaz, 1757-1831; Pott, August, 1806-1883; Pressel, Gustav, 1827-1890; Proch, Heinrich; Prume, Fr. (François), 1816-1849; Purcell, Henry, 1659-1695; Quantz, Johann Joachim, 1697-1773; Rauzzini, Venanzio, 1746-1810; Redern, Friedrich Wilhelm von, 1802-1883; Reeve, William, 1757-1815; Reicha, Anton, 1770-1836; Reid, John, 1721-1807; Reinecke, Carl, 1824-1910; Relfe, J. (John), 1763-approximately 1837; Relfe, Lupton, 1805-; Righini, Vincenzo, 1756-1812; Ritter, Peter, 1763-1846; Rosetti, Antonio, approximately 1750-1792; Rosselli, Agrippino, active 1784-1800; Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868; Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, 1712-1778; Rowlandson, Thomas, 1756-1827; Rummel, Christian, 1787-1849; St.-Lubin, Léon de; Sale, John, 1758-1827; Salieri, Antonio, 1750-1825; Sander, Johann Daniel, 1759-1826; Sarti, Giuseppe, 1729-1802; Satter, Gustave, 1832-1879; Sattler, Heinrich, 1811-1891; Schaffner, Nicolaus Albert, approximately 1790-; Schall, Claus Nielsen, 1757-1835; Schetky, G. (George), 1776-1831; Schmidt, J. P. (Johann Philipp), 1779-1853; Schmittbaur, Joseph Aloys; Schneider, Friedrich, 1786-1853; Schoeberlein, Ludwig; Schroeter, Johann Samuel, approximately 1752-1788; Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; Schuberth, Julius, 1804-1875; Schulz, F. A. (Friedrich August), 1810-1893; Schumann, Robert, 1810-1856; Shield, William, 1748-1829; Smart, George, 1776-1867; Smith, Robert Archibald, 1780-1829; Solms-Braunfels, Carl, Prinz zu, 1812-1875; Spix, Johann Baptist von, 1781-1826; Spohr, Louis, 1784-1859; Steibelt, Daniel, 1765-1823; Sterkel, Johann Franz Xaver, 1750-1817; Stern, Théophile, 1803-1886; Stevenson, John, 1761-1833; Stolze, Heinrich Wilhelm, 1801-1868; Storace, Stephen, 1762-1796; Strauss, Johann, 1804-1849; Struth, A. (Adam); Stumpf, Johann Christian; Sudre, François, 1787-1862; Szymanowska, Maria Agata Wołowska, 1789-1831; Tapray, Jean-François, 1738-approximately 1819; Tartini, Giuseppe, 1692-1770; Teschner, G. W. (Gustav Wilhelm), 1800-1883; Thomson, Mr. (George), 1757-1851; Tulou, Jean-Louis, 1786-1865; Ulybyshev, Aleksandr Dmitrievich, 1794-1858; Vanhal, Johann Baptist, 1739-1813; Vento, Mattia, 1735-1776; Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901; Victoria Mary Louisa, Duchess of Kent, 1786-1861; Vierling, Georg, 1820-1901; Vieuxtemps, Henri, 1820-1881; Viotti, Giovanni Battista, 1755-1824; Vischer, Friedrich Theodor, 1807-1887; Vogel, Johann Christoph, 1756-1788; Volckmar, W. (Wilhelm), 1812-1887; Voss, Charles, 1815-1882; Wackernagel, Philipp, 1800-1877; Wade, J. Augustine (Joseph Augustine), 1796-1845; Wallerstein, A. (Anton), 1813-1892; Walmisley, Thomas Attwood, 1814-1856; Webbe, Samuel, 1740-1816; Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826; Weigl, Joseph, 1766-1846; Weippert, E.; Werner, Gregor Joseph, 1693-1766; Wesley, Charles, 1757-1834; Westmeyer, Wilhelm, 1829-1880; Westmorland, John Fane, Earl of, 1784-1859; Weyse,